Guide to the Silvia DobsonPapers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Silvia Dobson papers
1945-1992
GEN MSS 409
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.12
(6 boxes)
Collection contains letters from American poet H.D. (Hilda Doolittle) to Silvia Dobson, letters from the British author Bryher to Silvia Dobson and her siblings Mervyn and Norah Dobson, as well as copies of several letters from Silvia to Bryher and letters from Kenneth Macpherson. Letters from H.D. document her life in Switzerland and London for nearly thirty years and include information about H.D.'s analysis with Sigmund Freud. Letters from Bryher document Bryher's life in Switzerland in the 1960's and 1970's, the Dobsons' lives in America, and Dobson's efforts to publish her work. Included among the correspondence are letters to H.D. from Norah, Mollie, and Mervyn Dobson, and Frances Gregg; and notes by Silvia H. Dobson. Included in the collection are typescripts of seven novels by Dobson: Feathers of Lead, Guests of Existence, Honor Bound or Shattering Mirror Images, The Hut of Laurel, The Kindhart Trap, Somebody and Nobody, and Spring Begins in Autumn. Also included is an untitled autobiography which describes her life as part of H. D.'s literary circle, her relief work during World War II, her relationship with H.D., her identity as a lesbian, and her later life living in America; and her untitled manuscript "Mirror for a Star, Star for a Mirror. H. D.'s letters to Silvia Dobson."
Dobson, Silvia, 1908-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Elizabeth Shoemaker throughRalph Sipper on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 1995 and 1997. Purchased from Silvia Dobson on the American Literature Fund, 1989.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Silvia Dobson(1908-)
Silvia Dobson, English-born author and friend of the poet H.D.
Scope and Contents
The papers contain letters from American poet H.D. (Hilda Doolittle) to Silvia Dobson, letters from the British author Bryher to Silvia Dobson and her siblings Mervyn and Norah Dobson, as well as copies of several letters from Silvia to Bryher and letters from Kenneth Macpherson. Letters from H.D. document her life in Switzerland and London for nearly thirty years and include information about H.D.'s analysis with Sigmund Freud. Letters from Bryher document Bryher's life in Switzerland in the 1960's and 1970's, the Dobsons' lives in America, and Dobson's efforts to publish her work. Included among the correspondence are letters to H.D. from Norah, Mollie, and Mervyn Dobson, and Frances Gregg; and notes by Silvia H. Dobson. Included in the collection are typescripts of seven novels by Dobson: Feathers of Lead, Guests of Existence, Honor Bound or Shattering Mirror Images, The Hut of Laurel, The Kindhart Trap, Somebody and Nobody, and Spring Begins in Autumn. Also included is an untitled autobiography which describes her life as part of H. D.'s literary circle, her relief work during World War II, her relationship with H.D., her identity as a lesbian, and her later life living in America; and her unpublished manuscript "Mirror for a Star, Star for a Mirror. H.D.'s letters to Silvia Dobson."
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence, 1945-1977. II. Writings, 1959-1992. III. Other Papers, undated. IV. "Mirror for a Star, Star for a Mirror: H. D.'s Letters to Silvia Dobson" material, 1935-1961.
Authors, English -- 20th Century; Lesbians; Lesbians' writings; Lesbian authors; Authors; LGBTQ resource; Bryher, 1894-1983; Dobson, Mervyn; Dobson, Silvia, 1908-; Dobson, Norah; H. D. (Hilda Doolittle), 1886-1961; Macpherson, Kenneth
- Correspondence, 1945-1977; Series I; 0.21; (1 box)
  - Letters from Bryher
    - To MervynDobson, 1971-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - To NorahDobson, 1945-1977 (Box 1, Folder 2-5)
    - To SilviaDobson, 1947-1977 (Box 1, Folder 6-9)
  - Letters from SilviaDobson
    - Copies of letters toBryher, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Writings, 1959-1992, undated; Series II; 1.47; (4 boxes)
  - Autobiography,typescript, corrected (pp. 290-291 are missing), 1992 April 1 (Box 2, Folder 11-20)
  - Feathers of Lead, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 2, Folder 21-27)
  - Guests of Existence, typescript,corrected, circa 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 28-41)
  - Honor Bound or Shattering Mirror Images ,typescript, corrected, undated (Box 3, Folder 42-50)
  - The Hut of Laurel, typescript,corrected, 1959 June 24 (Box 4, Folder 51-58)
  - The Kindhart Trap, typescript,corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 59-67)
  - Somebody and Nobody, typescript,corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 68-72)
  - Spring Begins in April, typescipt, corrected (pp.72-80 are missing), undated (Box 5, Folder 73-80)
- Other Papers, undated; Series III; 1
  - Empty folder inscribedwith holograph notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 81)
- "Mirror for a Star, Star for a Mirror: H. D.'s Letters to Silvia Dobson"material, 1935-1961; Series IV; 0.42; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains original and copies of letters from H.D. to Silvia Dobson. Also included in the correspondence are letters to H.D. from Norah, Mollie, and Mervyn Dobson, and Frances Gregg; letters from Kenneth Macpherson to Dobson; and notes by Silvia H. Dobson. The material was compiled by Dobson and entitled "Mirror for a Star, Star for a Mirror: H.D.'s Letters toSilvia Dobson."
  - Copies of letters from HDto Dobson, letters 1-42, File I, pages 1-125, 1934-May 1935, undated (Box 6, Folder 82)
  - Original letters from HDto SHD, letters 43-77, File II, pages 125-259, Spring 1935-Winter 1937 (Box 6, Folder 83)
  - Original letters from HDto SHD, letters 78-120, File III, pages 259-388, 1939-September 1944 (Box 6, Folder 84)
  - Copies of letters from HDto SHD, letters 121-152, File IV, pages 289-490; and letters from Bryher,Autumn 1944-1947, undated (Box 6, Folder 85)
  - Copies of letters from HDto SHD, letters 154-201, File V, pages 491-598, including letters from Bryher,pages 491-598, Spring 1947-Winter 1951, undated (Box 6, Folder 86)
  - Original letters from HDto SHD, letters 203-255, File VI, "the last nine magic years," pages 599-700(some from Brhyer), 1952-1961 (Box 6, Folder 87)